Inventory of the Kurt Werner Schaechter Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Kurt Werner Schaechter Collection
1933-2006
2007C4
Schaechter, Kurt Werner
54 manuscript boxes 21.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Acquired in 2007, the Kurt Werner Schaechter Collection in the Hoover Institution Archives consists primarily of photocopies made by Schaechter of documents from French state archives. These copies relate to the role played by the Vichy France government in the internment of refugees during the Second World War, and the deportation of many such refugees, especially Jews, toward Auschwitz and other Nazi concentration camps.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Chronology
1921 Born, Vienna, Austria
1938 Due to Nazi persecution of Austrian Jews following the incorporation of Austria into the German Reich, the Schaechter family leaves Vienna and settles in France
1939-1940 Mobilized into French army, trained in North Africa, and sent to Narvik, Norway
1943 Father is deported and killed in Sobibór
1944 Mother is deported and killed in Auschwitz
1950s-1970s Ran import-export company specializing in musical instruments
1991-1992 Conducted archival research in Toulouse, France on Vichy-era internments and deportations
1992 Went public with his copies of archival documents, becoming the center of a controversy regarding access to these and other documents
2003 Lawsuit initiated by Schaecter against the Socié té Nationale des Chemins de fer Français is ruled invalid by a French court under the terms of a statute of limitations applying to such cases
2006 Inaugurated plaque at a local railway station commemorating those deported by Vichy government
2007 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired in 2007, the Kurt Werner Schaechter Collection in the Hoover Institution Archives consists primarily of photocopies made by Schaechter of documents from French state archives. These copies relate to the role played by the Vichy government in the internment of refugees during the Second World War, and the deportation of many such refugees, especially Jews, toward Auschwitz and other Nazi death camps.
The son of Austrian Jews who were victims of the Nazis, Schaechter undertook a personal mission to document the complicity of the Vichy government in the Holocaust. He became particularly interested in the part played by the French national railroads in transporting interned Jewish and other refugees into German hands, and in the general subject of Vichy collaboration with the Nazis in this period. Schaechter's decision to file suit against the SNCF (Société Nationale des Chemins de fer Français) received wide media attention in France and elsewhere in the early 1990s, as did his decision to make public the documents he had photocopied. His lawsuit was ultimately unsuccessful-a French court ruled that his case had been brought too long after the events themselves-and the charges he made regarding access to French archival sources were challenged by many French historians of the Vichy period, who maintained that Schaechter's assertions regarding French collaboration in deportations had already been largely revealed by French and other historians in the 1970s and 1980s.
The materials in the collection will be of value to researchers interested in the controversies surrounding Schaechter's lawsuit and his decision to make archival documents available by copying and publishing them. The materials require some explanation as to their nature and Schaechter's description and arrangement of them. A large number of copies are stamped "secret," but are not considered to be classified. Furthermore, many of the photocopies cannot be assumed to be exact copies of French archival documents. Schaechter compiled and published large numbers of these copies under the auspices of his own foundation, E.T.H.I.C. (Enquête sur la Tragique Histoire des Internements dans les Camps en France). In doing so, he often combined documents or added his own descriptions. As a result, such copies must be considered facsimiles or composites, and need to be compared to the originals. Another factor that may cause confusion is Schaechter's use of the term "originaux", which he employed to describe the master copies that he later duplicated, and not the archival documents themselves. A large number of true copies are part of the collection, and these contain significant information about internments and deportations in the Vichy period.
It should be noted that there are many duplicates in the collection, as Schaechter made numerous sets of the same photocopied documents for use in his lawsuit and for other purposes. Different descriptions were added by Schaechter to these copies, depending on the circumstance, and they have been preserved inasmuch as they shed light on his polemics with others and his research activities in general.
The collection also contains correspondence, including some open letters addressed to French politicians, and a number of writings by Schaechter, including several historical plays. Details on Schaechter's lawsuit and other activities, as well as information on the fate of his parents, can be found in the Biographical File series.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Jews.; World War, 1939-1945--Concentration camps.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); France--History--German occupation, 1940-1945.
Related Material
Klaus Barbie pre-trial records, Hoover Institution Archives
Container List
- Biographical file, 1979-2006. (Box 1)
  Includes autobiography and family history, clippings, laws pertaining to French archives, and list of historians and supporters
  - Autobiography and family history, 1993-2006 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings, 1992-2006 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Laws pertaining to French archives, 1979 (Folder 1: 3)
  - List of historians and other supporters, circa 2000 (Folder 1: 4)
- Correspondence, 1989-1999. (Box 1)
  Contains letters and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General, 1991-1998 (Folder 1)
    - A-K, 1991-1998 (Folder 1: 5)
    - L-Z, 1991-1995 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Unidentified, 1992-1999 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Azéma, Charles, 1994 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Boutros Ghali, Boutros, 1993 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Chirac, Jacques, 1999 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Comédie de Saint Etienne (Daniel Benoin), 1993 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Corcuff, Marie-Andrée, 1997 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Cotta, Jacques, 1993 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Le Figaro (Max Clos), 1992 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Gerstein, Klaus, 1997-1998 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Giroud, Françoise, circa 1992 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Hehn, Jochen, 1997-1998 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Jacoby, Daniel, 1994 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Joffroy, Pierre, 1997 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Jouet, Jean-Claude, 1989-1992 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Juppé, Alain, 1993 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Klarsfeld, Serge, 1992 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Kriegel, Annie, 1992 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Leotard, François, 1993 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Libération (Annette Levy-Willard, Jean-Dominique Merchet), 1993-1998 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Marcel, François, 1993 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Ministè re de la Defense (France), 1997 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Minkowski, Alexandre, 1994 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Mitterand, François and Danielle, 1992 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Nicolas, Bernard, 1993 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Nowotny, Eva, 1993 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Pitteloud, Jean-François, 1999 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Poncelet, Christian, 1999 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Tribüne (Otto R. Romberg), 1993 (Folder 1: 34)
- Speeches and Writings, 1961-2006. (Box 1-2)
  Contains articles, plays, and other writings, arranged chronologically
  - Compilation of poetry and personal letters, 1960-1991. (Folder 1: 35)
    Typescript
  - "Die Nacht der langen Messer,", 1967 (Folder 1: 36)
  - "Ekkehard,", 1985 (Folder 1: 37)
  - "Guerillieros[sic] in der Sierra,", circa 1990 (Folder 2: 1)
  - "Michael Kohlhaas,", circa 1990. (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Der Putsch,", circa 1990. (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Rosa Luxemburg,", circa 1990. (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Der Skandal,", circa 1990 (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Die Spinne,", circa 1990 (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Ein wirtschaftliches und monetäres Projekt für Mitteleuropa,", 1995 (Folder 2: 7)
  - "Nouveaux algorithmes du triangle de Pascal et des nombres de combinaison,", 1996 February 14. (Folder 2: 8)
  - "Le problè me de l'accessibilité aux archives, en tant que droit de citoyen et droit de l'homme, et l'unique moyen de garantie de la démocratie, contre tout abus administratif et tout abus de pouvoir,", 1996 October. (Folder 2: 9)
  - "Pour une déclaration universelle de la dignité de la vie,", 1998 September 16. (Folder 3: 1)
  - "Le bataillon qui a combattu a Narvik en Norvè ge,", circa 2001. (Folder 3: 2)
  - "Le préfet Sabatier nommé par Papon état-il agent de la Gestapo? Sinon pourquoi aurait-il fait disparaître Kurt Gerstein, ce chrétien prussien qui tentait d'empêcher les livraisons de gaz mortel dans les camps?," Journal des combattants, 2004 November 27. (Folder 3: 3)
    Printed copy
  - "Frankreich das schwarze Buch,", circa 2006. (Box 3)
    - Chapter 1 (Folder 3: 4-6)
    - Chapter 3 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Chapter 4 (Folder 3: 8)
    - Chapter 5 (Folder 3: 9-10)
    - Chapter 6 (Folder 4: 1)
    - Chapter 8 (Folder 4: 2-3)
    - Chapter 9 (Folder 4: 4-6)
    - Chapters 27-31 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Chapters 32-33 (Folder 5: 1)
    - Chapters 34-36 (Folder 5: 2)
    - Chapters 37-40 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Chapters 41-44 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Chapter Z1 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Chapter Z2 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Chapter Z3 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Chapter Z4 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Chapter Z5 (Folder 5: 9)
    - Chapter Z6 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Miscellaneous illustrations (Folder 5: 11)
- Subject File, 1933-1998. (Box 6)
  Contains clippings and copies of archival documents, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Bettencourt, André, 1995 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Bousquet, René, 1992 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Dora (concentration camp), Germany, 1989-1996 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Dreyfus, Alfred (Folder 6: 4)
  - Gerstein, Kurt, 1933-1998 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Giraudoux, Jean, 1983-1986 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Maximoff (née Sabas), Carmen, 1945-1971 (Folder 6: 7)
  - Touvier, Paul, 1994 (Folder 6: 8)
- Writings by others, 1983-1996. (Box 6)
  Arranged by alphabetically by author
  - Guckes, Johann, circa 1996 (Folder 6: 9)
  - Vormeier, Barbara, circa 1983 (Folder 6: 10)
- Photographs, 1947-1996. (Box 6)
  Arranged chronologically
  - 1 print depicting Maurice Papon, 1947 (Folder 6: 11)
  - 12 prints depicting scenes of the former internment camp at Noé, France, 1996. (Folder 6: 12)
    Includes one print depicting a memorial to Jewish victims of the Nazis
- Computer disks, circa 2000. (Folder 6: 13-46)
  Thirty four floppy disks containing materials largely relating to the photocopying of French archival documents by Kurt Werner Schaechter
- Photocopies of archival documents, 1939-1950. (Box 7)
  Includes compilations published by E.T.H.I.C. (Enquête sur la Tragique Histoire des Internements dans les Camps en France); printed matter and other research materials; and related correspondence.
  - Tome I
    - Camp de Noé, 1944 (Folder 7: 1-2)
    - Cohn, Albert, 1941 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Goldmann, Emile, 1943 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Organisation Todt, Service Travail Obligatoire (S.T.0), 1943-1944 (Folder 7: 5-6)
    - Camp de Récébédou, 1941-1943 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Tome III
    - Camp de Récébédou, 1942-1943 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Camps de Récébédou, Vernet d'Ariè ge, et Noé, 1940-1944 (Folder 7: 9-10)
    - Dénonciations et enquêtes, 1942-1945 (Folder 8: 1)
    - Camps de Noé et Récébédou, 1941-1944 (Folder 8: 2)
    - Camp du Vernet d'Ariè ge, 1940 (Folder 8: 3)
    - Rapports de police et de gendarmerie, 1941-1943 (Folder 8: 4-5)
  - Tome V
    - Camp de Noé, 1943-1945 (Folder 8: 6)
    - Camps de Noé et du Vernet d'Ariè ge, 1941-1944 (Folder 8: 7)
    - Camp de Noé, îlot spécial, 1945-1946 (Folder 8: 8)
    - Comptabilité des camps, 1941 (Folder 8: 9)
    - Société Nationale des Chemins de fer Français (SNCF), 1940-1944 (Folder 8: 10)
  - Tome VI
    - Registre d'écrou, 1942-1943 (Folder 8: 11)
    - Registre d'écrou, 1942-1943 (Folder 9: 1)
    - Déportations et convois, 1942-1943 (Folder 9: 2-5)
  - Tome VII
    - Camp de Noé, 1943-1944 (Folder 9: 6-10)
    - Livre de mouvement des "hébergés" français, 1943-1944 (Folder 9: 9)
  - Tome VIII
    - Camp de Noé, 1944-1946 (Folder 10: 1-3)
    - Dossiers références, 1941-1944
      - Z-1 à Z-55 (Folder 10: 4)
      - Z-56 à Z-129 (Folder 10: 5)
      - Z-130 à Z-208 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Tome IX
    - Dossiers références, 1941-1944
      - Z-209 à Z-293 (Folder 10: 7)
      - Z-294 à Z-342 (Folder 10: 8)
  - Tome X
    - Dossiers références, 1941-1944
      - Z-343 à Z-444 (Folder 11: 1)
      - S (Folder 11: 2-3)
      - OA-1 à OA-60 (Folder 11: 4-5)
      - OB-61 à OB-174 (Folder 11: 6-8)
  - Tome XII
    - Dossiers références, 1941-1944
      - W-1 à W-138 (Folder 12: 1-4)
      - W-139 à W-301 (Folder 12: 5-8)
      - W-302 à W-507 (Folder 13: 1-6)
  - SNCF, 1942-1944 (Folder 13: 7)
  - Temoignages, 1941-1945 (Folder 13: 8)
  - Papon, Maurice, 1943-1946 (Folder 13: 9)
  - Anglais et américains, 1941-1944 (Folder 13: 10)
  - Camps secrets, 1943-1946 (Folder 13: 11-12)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 14: 1)
  - SNCF, 1941-1944 (Folder 14: 2-3)
  - Le train fantôme, 1944 (Folder 14: 4-5)
  - Îlot spécial, 1942-1946 (Folder 14: 6-8)
  - Gerstein, Kurt, 1943 (Folder 14: 9)
  - Camp de Noé, 1944-1949 (Folder 15: 1-2)
  - L'affaire Tulard, 1942-1949 (Folder 15: 3)
  - SNCF, 1941-1944 (Folder 15: 4)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 15: 5)
  - Elk, Salo (Salomon), 1941-1944 (Folder 15: 6)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 15: 7-8)
  - Camps secrets, 1943-1946 (Folder 15: 9-10)
  - Britanniques et américains, 1944 (Folder 15: 11)
  - Vichy, 1940-1944 (Folder 15: 12)
  - Sarraut, Albert et René Bousquet, 1939-1940 (Folder 16: 1)
  - Papon, Maurice, 1942-1944 (Folder 16: 2-6)
  - Auschwitz, 1943-1944 (Folder 16: 7)
  - Frydman, David, 1942-1944 (Folder 16: 8)
  - Dossiers références, 1939-1949 (Folder 16)
    - H-I (Folder 16: 9)
    - J (Folder 16: 10)
    - JL-1 (Folder 16: 11)
    - R (Folder 16: 12-13)
    - T (Folder 16: 14)
    - T (Folder 17: 1)
    - U (Folder 17: 2)
    - V (Folder 17: 3)
    - VC-VD (Folder 17: 4)
  - Papon, Maurice, 1942-1946 (Folder 17: 5)
  - Îlot spécial, 1940-1946 (Folder 17: 6)
  - Sarraut, Albert, 1939 (Folder 17: 7)
  - Camp de Noé, 1944-1946 (Folder 17: 8)
  - Le train fantôme, 1944 (Folder 18: 1)
  - SNCF, 1940-1950 (Folder 18: 2)
  - Îlot spécial, 1944-1947 (Folder 18: 3-4)
  - Coinaud, Albert et famille, 1940-1945 (Folder 18: 5-6)
  - Camps de Noé et Récébédou, 1944-1946 (Folder 18: 7)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 18: 6)
  - Dossiers originaux, 1939-1946 (Folder 19)
    - E (Folder 19: 1-2)
    - F (Folder 19: 2-11)
    - F (Folder 20: 1-4)
    - I (Folder 20: 5-7)
    - J (Folder 20: 8)
    - JL (Folder 20: 9-10)
    - VS (Folder 20: 11)
  - Sarraut, Albert, 1939-1944 (Folder 21: 1)
  - Camp de Noé, 1943 (Folder 21: 2)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 21: 3-10)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 22: 1-5)
  - Camps de Noé et Récébédou, 1940-1946 (Folder 22: 6-8)
  - Bousquet, René, 1943-1946 (Folder 22: 9)
  - Sarraut, Albert, 1939-1940 (Folder 22: 10)
  - Le train fantôme, 1944 (Folder 22: 11)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 23: 1-8)
  - Le train fantôme, 1944 (Folder 23: 9)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 24: 1-19)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 25: 1-3)
  - Dossiers généraux, 1939-1946
    - A (Folder 25: 4)
    - B (Folder 25: 5)
    - C (Folder 25: 6)
    - D, H (Folder 25: 7)
    - E (Folder 25: 8)
    - F (Folder 25: 9)
    - G (Folder 25: 10)
    - K (Folder 25: 11)
    - L (Folder 25: 12)
    - N (Folder 25: 13)
    - P (Folder 25: 14)
    - Q (Folder 26: 1)
    - R (Folder 26: 2)
    - S (Folder 26: 3)
    - T (Folder 26: 4)
    - U, V (Folder 26: 5)
    - W (Folder 26: 6)
    - X (Folder 26: 7)
    - Y (Folder 26: 8)
    - Z (Folder 26: 9)
    - AA (Folder 26: 10-11)
    - BB (Folder 26: 12)
    - CC (Folder 26: 13)
    - EE (Folder 26: 14)
    - HH (Folder 27: 1)
    - JJ (Folder 27: 2)
    - KK (Folder 27: 3)
    - LL (Folder 27: 4)
    - MM (Folder 27: 5)
    - OO, SS, TT (Folder 27: 6)
    - WW (Folder 27: 7)
    - YY (Folder 27: 8)
    - ZZ (Folder 27: 9)
    - I (Folder 27: 10)
    - II (Folder 27: 11-12)
    - III (Folder 28: 1)
    - IV (Folder 28: 2-3)
    - V (Folder 28: 4-5)
    - VI (Folder 28: 6-7)
    - VII (Folder 28: 8-9)
  - Dossiers originaux, 1939-1946 (Folder 29)
    - D (Folder 29: 1)
    - E (Folder 29: 2)
    - F (Folder 29: 3)
    - G (Folder 29: 4)
    - H (Folder 29: 5)
    - I (Folder 29: 6-7)
    - M (Folder 29: 8)
    - W (Folder 29: 9-11)
    - X (Folder 29: 12)
    - X (Folder 30: 1-3)
    - Z (Folder 30: 4-5)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 30: 6-11)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 31: 1-10)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 32: 1-5)
  - Le train fantôme, 1944 (Folder 32: 6)
  - Papon, Maurice, 1942-1944 (Folder 32: 7-11)
  - Le train fantôme, 1944 (Folder 33: 1)
  - Sarraut, Albert, 1939-1940 (Folder 33: 2)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 33: 3-10)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 34: 1-12)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 35: 1-11)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 36: 1-12)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 37: 1-6)
  - Le train fantôme, 1944 (Folder 37: 7)
  - Archives Klarsfeld, 1944 (Folder 37: 8)
  - Organisation Todt, 1943-1944 (Folder 37: 9)
  - Camps de Noé et du Vernet d'Ariè ge, 1941-1944 (Folder 37: 10-11)
  - Camp de Noé (Folder 38: 1)
  - Sarraut, Albert, 1939-1940 (Folder 38: 2)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 38: 3-10)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 39: 1-11)
  - Îlot spécial, 1944-1947 (Folder 40: 1-5)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 40: 6-10)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 41: 1-9)
  - Le train fantôme, 1944 (Folder 41: 10)
  - Dossiers références, 1939-1949 (Folder 42)
    - A (Folder 42: 1-3)
    - B (Folder 42: 5-10)
    - C (Folder 43: 1)
    - D (Folder 43: 2-5)
  - Belges, 1943-1946 (Folder 43: 6-7)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 43: 8-9)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 44: 1-10)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 45: 1-10)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 46: 1-9)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 47: 1-10)
  - Dossiers originaux, 1939-1946 (Folder 48)
    - BB (Folder 48: 1)
    - CC (Folder 48: 2)
    - F (Folder 48: 3)
    - J (Folder 48: 4-5)
    - S (Folder 48: 6-7)
    - U (Folder 48: 8)
    - V (Folder 48: 9-10)
    - W (Folder 48: 11-12)
    - W (Folder 49: 1)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 49: 2-9)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 50: 1-10)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 51: 1-11)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 52: 1-10)
  - Internements et déportations, 1939-1946 (Folder 53: 1-9)
- Incremental Materials (Folder 54)